I am sorry I cannot show you my face,
أنا آسف لا أستطيع أن أريكم وجهي،
because if I do, the bad guys will come for me.
لأنني إذا فعلت ذلك، سيأتون الأشرار ليأخذوني .
My journey started 14 years ago.
بدأت رحلتي قبل 14 عاماً.
I was a young reporter. I had just come out of college.
كنت شاباً مراسلاً . تخرجت وقتها من الكلية
Then I got a scoop.
ثم حصلت على سبق صحفي
The scoop was quite a very simple story.
السبق صحفي كان قصة بسيطة جداً.
Police officers were taking bribes
ضباط الشرطة كانوا يتقاضون رشاوى
from hawkers who were hawking on the streets.
من الباعة المتجولين الذين كانوا يتجولون في الشوارع.
As a young reporter, I thought that I should do it
كمراسل شباب، اعتقدت أنني يجب أن أفعل ذلك
in a different way, so that it has a maximum impact,
بطريقة مختلفة، ليكون لها أقصى قدر من التأثير،
since everybody knew that it was happening,
حيث أن الجميع كان يعلم بما يحدث،
and yet there was nothing that was keeping it out of the system.
ورغم ذلك لم يكن هناك شيء يردعه.
So I decided to go there
لذا قررت أن اذهب إلى هناك
and act as a seller.
وأتصرف كبائع.
As part of selling, I was able to document
كجزء من البيع، تمكنت من توثيق
the hard core evidence.
الدليل الحتمي.
The impact was great.
التأثير كان كبيراً.
It was fantastic.
كان رائعاً.
This was what many call immersion journalism,
كان هذا ما يسميه الكثيرون انغمار الصحافة ،
or undercover journalism.
أو الصحافة السرية.
I am an undercover journalist.
أنا مراسل سري.
My journalism is hinged on three basic principles:
صحافتي تتوقف على ثلاثة مبادئ أساسية:
naming, shaming and jailing.
التسمية والتشهير، والحبس.
Journalism is about results.
الصحافة هي النتائج.
It's about affecting your community or your society
هي كيفية التأثير في بيئتك أو مجتمعك
in the most progressive way.
بالطريقة الأكثر تقدمية.
I have worked on this for over 14 years,
لقد عملت على ذلك لأكثر من 14 عاماً،
and I can tell you, the results are very good.
ويمكن أن أقول لكم، النتائج جيدة جداً.
One story that comes to mind
قصة واحدة تتبادر إلى ذهني
in my undercover pieces
في أعمالي السرية
is "Spirit Child."
هي"روح الطفل."
It was about children who were born with deformities,
وكانت عن الأطفال الذين ولدوا مع تشوهات،
and their parents felt that once they were born
وأولياء أمورهم شعروا بمجرد أنهم ولدوا
with those deformities,
مع تلك التشوهات،
they were not good enough to live in the society,
أنهم ليسوا جيدين بما فيه الكفاية للعيش في المجتمع،
so they were given some concoction to take
فأعطوهم بعض الخلطات السامة
and as a result they died.
ونتيجة لذلك قد توفوا.
So I built a prosthetic baby,
لذا صنعت طفل صناعي رضيع
and I went into the village,
وذهبت إلى القرية،
pretended as though this baby had been born
تظاهرت كما لو كان هذا الطفل قد ولد
with a deformity, and here was the guys who do the killing.
مشوه، وهنا كان الرجال الذين يقومون بالقتل.
They got themselves ready.
جهزوا أنفسهم.
In their bids to kill, I got the police on standby,
في عروضهم للقتل، جعلت الشرطة على أهبة الاستعداد،
and they came that fateful morning
و جاءوا في ذلك الصباح المصيري
to come and kill the child.
ليأتوا و يقتلوا الطفل.
I recall how they were seriously boiling the concoction.
وأذكر كيف أنهم كانوا يغلون الخلطة السامة
They put it on fire. It was boiling hot,
وضعوها على النار. كانت ساخنة لدرجة الغليات،
getting ready to give to the kids.
تُجهز لإعطائها للأطفال.
Whilst this was going on, the police I had alerted,
في حين أن هذا كان يحدث، الشرطة التي استنفرتها،
they were on standby,
كانوا على أهبة الاستعداد،
and just as the concoction was ready,
وحالما جهزت الخلطة،
and they were about to give it to the kids,
وكانوا على وشك إعطائها للأطفال،
I phoned the police,
اتصلت بالشرطة،
and fortunately they came and busted them.
ومن حسن الحظ أنها جاءت وضبطتهم.
As I speak now, they are before the courts.
وأنا أتكلم الآن، هم أمام المحاكم.
Don't forget the key principles:
لا تنسى المبادئ الرئيسية:
naming, shaming and jailing.
التسمية والتشهير، والحبس.
The court process is taking place,
اجراءات المحاكمة تنعقد الآن،
and I'm very sure at the end of the day
وأنا واثق جداً أنه في نهاية اليوم
we will find them, and we will put them
سنجدهم، وسوف نضعهم
where they belong too.
إلى حيث ينتمون
Another key story that comes to mind,
قصة رئيسية أخرى تتبادر إلى ذهني،
which relates to this spirit child phenomenon,
مرتبطة بهذه الظاهرة "روح الطفل"،
is "The Spell of the Albinos."
هي "سحر المصابين بالمهق."
I'm sure most of you may have heard, in Tanzania,
أنا متأكد من أن معظمكم قد سمع، في تنزانيا،
children who are born with albinism
الأطفال الذين يولدون بالمهاق
are sometimes considered as being unfit
يعتبرون في بعض الأحيان غير صالحين
to live in society.
للعيش في المجتمع.
Their bodies are chopped up with machetes
أجسادهم مقطعة بالسواطير
and are supposed to be used for some concoctions
ومن المحتمل أن يتم استخدامها في بعض الخلطات الدوائيه
or some potions for people to get money --
أو بعض الجرعات للناس للحصول على المال-
or so many, many stories people would tell about it.
أو الكثير ، الكثير من القصص التي يقولونها الناس حول هذا الموضوع.
It was time to go undercover again.
كان الوقت قد حان للذهاب للعمل كمراسل سري مرة أخرى.
So I went undercover as a man who was interested
فذهبت متخفياً كرجل مهتم
in this particular business, of course.
في هذا النوع من الأعمال، بالطبع.
Again, a prosthetic arm was built.
مرة أخرى، بُنَيت ذراع اصطناعية.
For the first time, I filmed on hidden camera
للمرة الأولى، صورت بكاميرا خفية
the guys who do this, and they were ready to buy the arm
الرجال الذين فعلوا هذا، وكانوا على استعداد لشراء الذراع
and they were ready to use it to prepare
وكانوا على استعداد استخدامها لإعداد
those potions for people.
تلك الجرعات للناس.
I am glad today the Tanzanian government has taken action,
ويسرني اليوم أن الحكومة التنزانية قد اتخذت إجراءات،
but the key issue is that the Tanzanian government
لكن المشكلة الرئيسية هي أن الحكومة التنزانية
could only take action because the evidence was available.
تمكنت فقط من اتخاذ إجراء لأن الأدلة توفرت.
My journalism is about hard core evidence.
صحافتي تتمحور حول الأدلة القاطعة.
If I say you have stolen, I show you the evidence
إذا قلت أنك قد سرقت، أُظهر لك الأدلة
that you have stolen.
التي تثبت بأنك قد سرقت.
I show you how you stole it
أُظهر لك كيف سرقت
and when, or what you used
ومتى، أو ماذا استخدمت
what you had stolen to do.
ماذا سرقت للقيام به.
What is the essence of journalism if it doesn't benefit society?
ما هو جوهر الصحافة إذا كانت لا تفيد المجتمع؟
My kind of journalism is a product
نوع صحافتي هو نتاج
of my society.
مجتمعي.
I know that sometimes
أنا أعلم أنه في بعض الأحيان
people have their own criticisms
الناس لديهم انتقاداتهم الخاصة بهم
about undercover journalism.
حول الصحافة السرية.
(Video) Official: He brought out some money from his pockets
(فيديو) مسؤول: أخرج بعض المال من جيبه
and put it on the table,
ووضعها على الطاولة،
so that we should not be afraid.
لكي لا نكون خائفين.
He wants to bring the cocoa and send it to Cote d'Ivoire.
أنه يريد أن يجلب الكاكاو وإرساله إلى "ساحل العاج".
So with my hidden intention, I kept quiet.
لذا مع نيتي المخفية، ظللت هادئاً.
I didn't utter a word.
لم أنطق بكلمة.
But my colleagues didn't know.
ولكن زملائي لم يعرفوا.
So after collecting the money,
لذا بعد جمع المال،
when he left, we were waiting for him to bring the goods.
عندما غادر، كنا ننتظره ليجلب البضائع.
Immediately after he left, I told my colleagues that
فورا بعد أن غادر، قلت لزملائي أن
since I was the leader of the group,
بما أنني كنت قائد الفريق،
I told my colleagues that if they come,
قلت لزملائي أنهم إذا جاءوا،
we will arrest them.
سوف نقبض عليهم.
Second official: I don't even know the place called [unclear].
المسؤول الثاني: لا أعرف حتى ماذا يدعى المكان[غير واضح].
I've never stepped there before.
لم أذهب هناك من قبل.
So I'm surprised.
لذا أنا مندهش.
You see a hand counting money just in front of me.
تشاهد يد تعد المال أمامي تماماً.
The next moment, you see the money in my hands,
اللحظة التالية، ترى المال في يدي،
counting, whereas I have not come into contact with anybody.
أعد، في حين أنني لم اتواصل مع أي شخص.
I have not done any business with anybody.
أنا لم أفعل أي عمل مع أي شخص.
Reporter: When Metro News contacted investigative reporter
المحرر: عندما اتصلت "أخبار مترو" بمراسل التحقيق
Anas Aremeyaw Anas for his reaction,
"أنس أريميياو أنس" لمعرفة رد فعله،
he just smiled and gave this video extract
ابتسم فقط وأعطى هذا الفيديو المختصر
he did not use in the documentary recently shown onscreen.
الذي لم يستخدمه في الفيلم الوثائقي الذي عرض مؤخرا على الشاشة.
The officer who earlier denied involvement
الضابط الذي نفي في وقت سابق التورط
pecks a calculator to compute the amount of money
يحمل آلة حاسبة لحساب مبلغ المال
they will charge on the cocoa to be smuggled.
الذي سيتقاضونه على تهريب الكاكاو
Anas Aremeyaw Anas: This was another story on anticorruption.
"أنس أريميياو أنس": كانت هذه قصة أخرى عن مكافحة الفساد.
And here was him, denying.
وهنا هو، ينفي.
But you see, when you have the hard core evidence,
لكن أنت ترى، عندما يكون لديك أدلة قاطعة،
you are able to affect society.
تكون لديك القدرة على التأثير في المجتمع.
Sometimes these are some of the headlines that come. (Music)
في بعض الأحيان هذه هي بعض العناوين التي تأتي. (موسيقى)
[I will curse Anas to death]
[سوف ألعن أنس حتى الموت]
[Anas Lies]
[أنس يكذب]
[Alarm Blows Over Anas' News for Cash Video]
[ ضربات ناقوس الخطر بسبب أخبار أنس عن فيديو المال ]
[Agenda Against Top CEPS Officials Exposed]
[انكشاف أجندة ضد مسؤولين كبار "سيبس"]
[Anas Operates with Invisible Powers?]
[أنس يعمل مع قوي غير مرئية؟]
[Gov't Wobbles Over Anas Video]
[الحكومة تهتز بسبب فيديو أنس]
[Hunting the Hunter]
[صيد الصياد]
[Anas 'Bribe' Men in Court]
[المرتشون من أنس في المحكمة]
[15 Heads Roll Over Anas Tape]
[15 رأسا تتدحرج بسبب فيديو أنس]
[Finance Minister Backs Anas]
[وزير المالية يدعم أنس]
[11 Given Queries Over Anas' Story]
[11 أعطوا افادات حول قصة أنس]
[GJA Stands By Anas]
["جيا" تقف إلى جانب أنس]
[Prez. Mills Storms Tema Harbour Over Anas Video]
["بيريز ميلز" يعصف "ميناء تيما" بسبب فيديو أنس]
["Late Prof. John Evans Atta Mills: Former president of Ghana"]
["الراحل البروفيسور جون إيفانز آتا ميلز: رئيس غانا السابق"]
John Evans Atta Mills: What Anas says
جون إيفانس آتا ميلز: ما يقوله أنس
is not something which is unknown to many of us,
ليس بالشيء الخفي للكثيرين منا،
but please, those of you who are agents,
لكن رجاءً، من كان منكم عميلاً
and who are leading the customs officers into temptation,
والذين يغرون ضباط الجمارك.
I'm telling you, Ghana is not going to say
أنا أقول لكم، غانا لن تقول لكم
any good things to you about this.
أي شيء جيد عن هذا الشيء.
AAA: That was my president.
أي أي أي: هذا كان رئيس بلدي.
I thought that I couldn't come here
أعتقدت أنه لا يمكن أن آتي هنا
without giving you something special.
دون أن أعطيكم شيئا خاصا.
I have a piece, and I'm excited that
لدي قطعة، وأشعر بسعادة غامرة
I'm sharing it for the first time with you here.
أنا أشاركها معكم لأول مرة هنا.
I have been undercover in the prisons.
كنت صحفي سري في السجون.
I have been there for a long time.
لقد كنت هناك لفترة طويلة.
And I can tell you, what I saw is not nice.
وأستطيع أن أقول لكم، ما رأيت ليس لطيفاً.
But again, I can only affect society
لكن مرة أخرى، أنا فقط أؤثر على المجتمع
and affect government if I bring out the hard core evidence.
وأؤثر على الحكومة إذا أظهرت الأدلة القاطعة.
Many times, the prison authorities have denied
مرات عديدة، نفت سلطات السجن
ever having issues of drug abuse,
قطعاً وجود قضايا تعاطي المخدرات،
issues of sodomy, so many issues they would deny
قضايا اللواط، الكثير من القضايا والتي انكروا
that it ever happens.
أنها قد حدثت في أي وقت مضى.
How can you obtain the hard core evidence?
كيف يمكنك الحصول على الأدلة القاطعة؟
So I was in the prison. ["Nsawan Prison"]
كنت في السجن. ["سجن نساوان"]
Now, what you are seeing is a pile of dead bodies.
الآن، ما تراه هو كومة من الجثث.
Now, I happen to have followed one of my inmates,
الآن،تصادف أنني كنت ألاحق أحد زملائي السجناء،
one of my friends, from his sick bed till death,
وأحد من أصدقائي، من سرير مرضه حتى الموت،
and I can tell you it was not a nice thing at all.
ويمكن أن أقول لكم أنه لم يكن شيء جميل على الإطلاق.
There were issues of bad food being served
كانت هناك قضايا تتعلق برداءة الطعام الذي يقدم
as I recall that some of the food I ate
كما أذكر أن بعض الطعام الذي أكلته
is just not good for a human being.
ليست جيدا لإنسان.
Toilet facilities: very bad.
المراحيض: سيئة جداً.
I mean, you had to queue to get proper toilets to attend --
أعني، كان يجب أن تقف في طابور للحصول على مراحيض مناسبة -
and that's what I call proper,
وهذا ما أسميه مناسب،
when four of us are on a manhole.
عندما يكون أربعة منا على فتحة مجاري واحدة.
It is something that if you narrate it to somebody,
هذا أمر إذا ما رويته لشخص ما،
the person wouldn't believe it.
فلن يصدق ذلك.
The only way that you can let the person believe
الطريقة الوحيدة التي يمكنك أن تدع الشخص يصدق
is when you show hard core evidence.
هو عندما تقوم بإظهار أدلة قاطعة.
Of course, drugs were abundant.
بالطبع، المخدرات كانت وفيرة.
It was easier to get cannabis, heroin and cocaine,
كان من السهل الحصول على الحشيش والهيروين والكوكايين،
faster even, in the prison than outside the prison.
أسرع حتى، في السجن من خارج السجن.
Evil in the society is an extreme disease.
الشر في المجتمع مرض شديد.
If you have extreme diseases,
إذا كان لديك الأمراض شديدة،
you need to get extreme remedies.
فأنت بحاجة للحصول على سبل معالجة شديدة.
My kind of journalism might not fit in other continents
نوع صحافتي قد لا يصلح في القارات الأخرى
or other countries,
أو في بلدان أخرى،
but I can tell you, it works in my part of the continent
لكن يمكن أن أقول لكم، أنها تعمل في جزء قارتي
of Africa, because usually, when people talk
من أفريقيا، لأنه عندما يتحدث الناس عادة،
about corruption, they ask, "Where is the evidence?
حول الفساد، يسألون، "أين هي الأدلة؟
Show me the evidence."
أرني الأدلة. "
I say, "This is the evidence."
أقول، "هذه هي الأدلة".
And that has aided in me putting a lot of people behind bars.
وهاذا ساعدني في وضع كثير من الناس وراء القضبان.
You see, we on the continent are able
أنت تعلم، نحن في القارة قادرين على
to tell the story better because we face the conditions
أن نروي القصة بصورة أفضل نظراً لأننا نواجه الظروف
and we see the conditions.
ونحن نرى الظروف.
That is why I was particularly excited
هذا السبب الذي كنت متحمساً لأجله
when we launched our "Africa Investigates" series
عندما بدأنا بسلسلة " أفريقيا تستقصي"
where we investigated a lot of African countries.
حيث أننا أجرينا تحقيقا في الكثير من البلدان الأفريقية.
As a result of the success of the "Africa Investigates" series,
نتيجة لنجاح هذه السلسلة "أفريقيا تستقصي"،
we are moving on to World Investigates.
نحن نتجه إلى "التحقيق في العالم".
By the end of it, a lot more bad guys
بنهاية الأمر، الكثير من الأشرار
on our continent will be put behind bars.
في قارتنا سوف يوضعون خلف القضبان.
This will not stop.
وهذا لن يتوقف.
I'm going to carry on with this kind of journalism,
أنا سأقوم بالأستمرار في هذا النوع من الصحافة،
because I know that when evil men destroy,
لأنني أعلم أنه عندما يدمر الأشرار
good men must build and bind.
الرجال الجيدون يجب أن يبنوا ويتحدوا.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Chris Anderson: Thank you. Thank you.
كريس أندرسون: شكرا لك. شكرا.
I have some questions for you.
لدى بعض الأسئلة لك.
How did you end up in jail? This was just a few weeks ago, I believe, yeah?
كيف انتهي بك المطاف في السجن؟ كان هذا في الأسابيع القليلة الماضية ، أعتقد، أليس كذلك؟
AAA: Sure. You know, undercover is all about
AAA: بالتأكيد. تعلمون، السرية كلها تتمحور حول
setting the priorities right, so we got people
تحديد الأولويات الصحيحة، حيث حصلنا على أناس
to take me to court.
ليأخذوني إلى المحكمة.
So I went through the very legal process,
فقد مررت خلال عملية قانونية جداً،
because at the end of the day, the prison authorities
لأنه في نهاية اليوم، سلطات السجن
want to check whether indeed you have been there or not,
تريد التحقق من ما إذا كنت في الواقع هناك أم لا،
and that's how I got in there.
و كيف وصلت إلى هناك.
CA: So someone sued you in court,
كريس: إذا شخص قاضاك في المحكمة،
and they took you there, and you were in remand custody
وأخذوك هناك، وكنت في الحبس رهن التحقيق
for part of it, and you did that deliberately.
لبعض الوقت، و فعلت ذلك عمدا.
AAA: Yes, yes.
AAA: نعم، نعم.
CA: Talk to me just about fear
كريس: حدثني فقط عن الخوف
and how you manage that,
وكيف تعاملت معه،
because you're regularly putting your life at risk.
لأنك كنت بانتظام تضع حياتك في خطر.
How do you do that?
كيف تفعل ذلك؟
AAA: You see, undercover is always a last resort.
AAA: حسنا، التخفي هو دائماً الحل الأخير.
Before we go undercover, we follow the rules.
قبل أن نذهب متخفيين، نتبع القواعد.
And I'm only comfortable and I'm purged of fear
أنا فقط أرتاح ولا أشعر بالخوف
whenever I am sure that all the steps
عندما أتأكد من أن جميع الخطوات
have been taken. I don't do it alone. I have a backup team
قد اتخذت. أنا لا أفعل ذلك وحدي. لدى فريق دعم
who help ensure that the safety and all the systems
يساعد على ضمان السلامة وجميع الاحتياطات
are put in place, but you've got to take
قد أتخذت ، لكن يجب أن تتخذ
very intelligent decisions whenever they are happening.
قرارات ذكية جداً كلما حدثت.
If you don't, you will end up losing your life.
إذا لم تفعل ذلك، سوف ينتهي بك ميتاً.
So yes, when the backup systems are put in place,
لذا نعم ، عندما يتم وضع الانظمة الاحتياطية في مكانها،
I'm okay, I go in. Risky, yes,
أنا بخير، واذهب. نعم، خطرة،نعم
but it's a hazard of a profession.
بل أنه مهنة خطرة
I mean, everybody has their hazard.
أعني كل إنسان له مجازافات.
And once you say that is yours,
ومتى ما قلت أن هذا هو لك،
you've got to take it, as and when it comes.
يجب أن تأخذه، كما يأتي ومتى ما أتى
CA: Well, you're an amazing human and you've done amazing work
"سي أي": حسنا، أنت إنسان مذهل ولقد قمت بعمل رائع
and you've taught us a story
ولقد علمتنا قصة
like no story I think any of us have heard before.
ليست مثل أي قصة أعتقد أن أي منا قد سمعها من قبل.
And we're appreciative. We salute you. Thank you so much, Anas.
ونحن نُقَدِرلك هذا. ونحن نحييك. شكرا جزيلا، أنس.
AAA: Thank you.
"أنس": شكرا لك.
CA: Thank you. Stay safe. (Applause)
"كريس": شكرا لك. ابقى آمناً. (تصفيق)